The following content is
provided under a Creative
Commons license.
Your support will help
MIT OpenCourseWare
continue to offer high quality
educational resources for free.
To make a donation or
view additional materials
from hundreds of MIT courses,
visit MIT OpenCourseWare
at ocw.mit.edu.
PROFESSOR: Today's topic
is regression analysis.
And this subject
is one that we're
going to cover it today
covering the mathematical and
statistical foundations
of regression
and focus particularly
on linear regression.
This methodology is perhaps
the most powerful method
in statistical modeling.
And the foundations
of it, I think,
are very, very important
to understand and master,
and they'll help you in any
kind of statistical modeling
exercise you might entertain
during or after this course.
And its popularity in
finance is very, very high,
but it's also a very
popular methodology
in all other disciplines
that do applied statistics.
So let's begin with setting up
the multiple linear regression
problem.
So we begin with a data set that
consists of data observations
on different cases,
a number of cases.
So we have n cases indexed by i.
And there's a single variable,
a dependent variable or response
variable, which is
the variable of focus.
And we'll denote that y sub i.
And together with that,
for each of the cases,
there are explanatory variables
that we might observe.
So the y_i's, the
dependent variables,
could be returns on stocks.
The explanatory variables could
be underlying characteristics
of those stocks
over a given period.
The dependent variable
could be the change
in value of an index, the S&P
500 index or the yield rate,
and the explanatory
variables can
be various macroeconomic
factors or other factors that
might be used to explain how
the response variable changes
and takes on its value.
Let's go through various
goals of regression analysis.
OK, first it can be
to extract or exploit
the relationship between
the dependent variable
and the independent variable.
And examples of
this are prediction.
Indeed, in finance
that's where I've
used regression analysis most.
We want to predict what's going
to happen and take actions
to take advantage of that.
One can also use
regression analysis
to talk about causal inference.
What factors are really
driving a dependent variable?
And so one can actually
test hypotheses
about what are true
causal factors underlying
the relationships
between the variables.
Another application is for
just simple approximation.
As mathematicians,
you're all very
familiar with how
smooth functions can
be-- that are smooth
in the sense of being
differentiable and bounded.
Those can be approximated
well by a Taylor series
if you have a function of
a single variable or even
a multivariable function.
So one can use
regression analysis
to actually approximate
functions nicely.
And one can also use
regression analysis
to uncover functional
relationships
and validate functional
amongst the variables.
So let's set up the
general linear model
from a mathematical
standpoint to begin with.
In this lecture, OK,
we're going to start off
with discussing ordinary
least squares, which
is a purely mathematical
criterion for how
you specify regression models.
And then we're going to turn to
the Gauss-Markov theorem which
incorporates some statistical
modeling principles there.
They're essentially
weak principles.
And then we will
turn to formal models
with normal linear
regression models,
and then consider extensions
of those to broader classes.
Now we're in the
mathematical context.
And a linear model is
basically attempting
to model the conditional
distribution of the response
variable y_i given the
independent variables x_i.
And the conditional distribution
of the response variable
is modeled simply
as a linear function
of the independent variables.
So the x_i's, x_(i,1)
through x_(i,p),
are the key explanatory
variables that relate
to the response
variables, possibly.
And the beta_1, beta_2,
beta_i, or beta_p,
are the regression
parameters which
would be used in defining
that linear relationship.
So this relationship has
residuals, epsilon_i,
basically where there's
uncertainty in the data--
whether it's either due to a
measurement error or modeling
error or underlying
stochastic processes that
are driving the error.
This epsilon_i is a
residual error variable
that will indicate how this
linear relationship varies
across the different n cases.
So OK, how broad are the models?
Well, the models
really are very broad.
First of all,
polynomial approximation
is indicated here.
It corresponds, essentially,
to a truncated Taylor
series approximation
to a functional form.
With variables that
exhibit cyclical behavior,
Fourier series can be applied
in a linear regression context.
How many people in here are
familiar with Fourier series?
Almost everybody.
So Fourier series
basically provide
a set of basis functions
that allow you to closely
approximate most functions.
And certainly with
bounded functions
that possibly have a
cyclical structure to them,
it provides a
complete description.
So we could apply
Fourier series here.
Finally, time series regressions
where the cases i one through n
are really indexes of different
time points can be applied.
And so the independent
variables can
be variables that are
observable at a given time point
or known at a given time.
So those can include lags
of the response variables.
So we'll see actually when
we talk about time series
that there's
autoregressive time series
models that can be specified.
And those are very broadly
applied in finance.
All right, so let's go through
what the steps are for fitting
a regression model.
First, one wants
to propose a model
in terms of what
is it that we have
to identify or be interested in
a particular response variable.
And critical here is
specifying the scale
of that response variable.
Choongbum was discussing
problems of modeling stock
prices.
If, say, y is the stock price?
Well, it may be that it's
more appropriate to consider
modeling it on a logarithmic
scale than on a linear scale.
Who can tell me why that
would be a good idea?
AUDIENCE: Because
the changes might
become more percent
changes in price
rather than absolute
changes in price.
PROFESSOR: Very good, yeah.
So price changes basically
on the percentage scale,
which log changes would be,
may be much better predicted
by knowing factors than
the absolute price level.
OK, and so we have
to have a collection
of independent variables,
which to include in the model.
And it's important
to think about how
general this set up is.
I mean, the
independent variables
can be functions, lag values
of the response variable.
They can be different
functional forms
of other independent variables.
So the fact that we're talking
about a linear regression model
here is it's not so limiting
in terms of the linearity.
We can really capture
lot of nonlinear behavior
in this framework.
So then third, we need to
address the assumptions
about the distribution of
the residuals, epsilon,
over the cases.
So that has to be specified.
Once we've set up
the model in terms
of identifying the response
of the explanatory variables
and the assumptions
underlying the distribution
of the residuals, we need to
specify a criterion for judging
different estimators.
So given a particular
setup, what we want to do
is be able to define a
methodology for specifying
the regression parameters
so that we can then
use this regression
model for prediction
or whatever our purpose is.
So the second
thing we want to do
is define a criterion
for how we might
judge different estimators of
the progression parameters.
We're going to go
through several of those.
And you'll see those-- least
squares is the first one,
but there are actually
more general ones.
In fact, the last
section of this lecture
on generalized estimators
will cover those as well.
Third, we need to characterize
the best estimator
and apply it to the given data.
So once we choose a
criterion for how good
an estimate of
regression parameters
is, then we have to have
a technology for solving
for that.
And then fourth, we need
to check our assumptions.
Now, it's very often the case
that at this fourth step, where
you're checking the
assumptions that you've made,
you'll discover features
of your data or the process
that it's modeling
that make you want
to expand upon your assumptions
or change your assumptions.
And so checking the
assumptions is a critical part
of any modeling process.
And then if necessary, modify
the model and assumptions
and repeat this process.
What I can tell you
is that this sort
of protocol for
how you fit models
is what I've applied
many, many times.
And if you are lucky in a
particular problem area,
the very simple
models will work well
with small changes
in assumptions.
But when you get
challenging problems,
then this item five
of modify the model
and/or assumptions is critical.
And in statistical
modeling, my philosophy
is you really want to,
as much as possible,
tailor the model to the
process you're modeling.
You don't want to fit a
square peg in a round hole
and just apply, say,
simple linear regression
to everything.
You want to apply it when
the assumptions are valid.
If the assumptions
aren't valid, maybe you
can change the
specification of the problem
so a linear model is still
applicable in a changed
framework.
But if not, then
you'll want to extend
to other kinds of models.
But what we'll be
doing-- or what
you will be doing if you do
that-- is basically applying
all the same principles
that are developed
in the linear
modeling framework.
OK, now let's see.
I wanted to make
some comments here
about specifying assumptions
for the residual distribution.
What kind of assumptions
might we make?
OK, would anyone like to
suggest some assumptions
you might make in
a linear regression
model for the residuals?
Yes?
What's your name, by the way?
AUDIENCE: My name is Will.
PROFESSOR: Will, OK.
Will what?
[? AUDIENCE: Ossler. ?]
PROFESSOR: [? Ossler, ?] great.
OK, thank you, Will.
AUDIENCE: It might
be-- or we might
want to say that the residual
might be normally distributed
and it might not depend too
much on what value of the input
variable we'd use.
PROFESSOR: OK.
Anyone else?
OK.
Well, that certainly
is an excellent place
to start in terms of starting
with a distribution that's
familiar.
Familiar is always good.
Although it's not something
that should be necessary,
but we know from some of
Choongbum's lecture areas
that Gaussian and
normal distributions
arise in many
settings where we're
taking basically sums of
independent, random variables.
And so it may be that these
residuals are like that.
Anyway, a slightly simpler
or weaker condition
is to use the Gauss-- what
are called in statistics
the Gauss-Markov assumptions.
And these are assumptions
where we're only
concerned with the means
or averages, statistically,
and the variances
of the residuals.
And so we assume that
there's zero mean.
So on average, they're not
adding a bias up or down
to the dependent variable.
And those have a
constant variance.
So the level of
uncertainty in our model
doesn't depend on the case.
And so indeed, if errors
on the percentage scale
are more appropriate, then
one could look at, say,
a time series of prices
that you're trying to model.
And it may be that
on the log scale,
that constant variance
looks much more appropriate
than on the original
scale, which would have--
And then a third attribute of
the Gauss-Markov assumptions
is that the residuals
are uncorrelated.
So now uncorrelated does
not mean independent
or statistically independent.
So this is a somewhat weak
condition, or weaker condition,
than independence
of the residuals.
But in the Gauss-Markov
setting, we're
just setting up
basically a reduced set
of assumptions that we might
apply to fit the model.
If we extend upon
that, we can then
consider normal linear
regression models,
which Will just suggested.
And in this case, those could
be assumed to be independent
and identically
distributed-- IID
is that notation for that-- with
Gaussian or normal with mean 0
and variance sigma squared.
We can extend upon
that to consider
generalized Gauss-Markov
assumptions where we maintain
still the zero mean
for the residuals,
but the general-- we might
have a covariance matrix which
does not correspond to
independent and identically
distributed random variables.
Now, let's see.
In the discussion of
probability theory,
we really haven't talked yet
about matrix-valued random
variables, right?
But how many people
in the class have
covered matrix-value or
vector-valued random variables
before?
OK, just a handful.
Well, a vector-valued
random variable,
we think of the
values of these n
cases for the dependent variable
to be an n-valued, an n-vector
of random variables.
And so we can
generalize the variance
of individual random variables
to the variance covariance
matrix of the collection.
And so you have a covariance
matrix characterizing
the variance of the n-vector
which gives us the-- the (i, j)
element gives us the
value of the covariance.
All right, let me put
the screen up and just
write that on the board so
that you're familiar with that.
All right, so we have
y_1, y_2, down to y_n,
our n values of our
response variable.
And we can basically talk
about the expectation
of that being equal to
mu_1, mu_2, down to mu_n.
And the covariance matrix
of y_1, y_2, down to y_n
is equal to a matrix
with the variance of y_1
in the upper 1, 1 element, and
the variance of y_2 in the 2,
2 element, and the variance of
y_n in the nth column and nth
row.
And in the (i,j)-th row, (i, j),
we have the covariance between
y_i and y_j.
So we're going to use matrices
to represent covariances.
And that's something
which I want everyone
to get very familiar
with because we're
going to assume that we
are comfortable with those,
and apply matrix algebra with
these kinds of constructs.
So the generalized
Gauss-Markov theorem
assumes a general
covariance matrix
where you can have
nonzero covariances
between the
independent variables
or the dependent variables
and the residuals.
And those can be correlated.
Now, who can come
up with an example
of why the residuals might
be correlated in a regression
model?
Dan?
OK.
That's a really good example
because it's nonlinear.
If you imagine sort of
a simple nonlinear curve
and you try to fit a
straight line to it,
then the residuals
from that linear fit
are going to be consistently
above or below the line
depending on where you are
in the nonlinearity, how
it might be fitting.
So that's one example
where that could arise.
Any other possibilities?
Well, next week we'll be talking
about some time series models.
And there can be time
dependence amongst variables
where there are some
underlying factors maybe
that are driving the process.
And those ongoing
factors can persist
in making the
linear relationship
over or under gauge
the dependent variable.
So that can happen as well.
All right, yes?
AUDIENCE: The Gauss-Markov
is just the diagonal case?
PROFESSOR: Yes, the Gauss-Markov
is simply the diagonal case.
And explicitly if we replace
y's here by the residuals,
epsilon_1 through
epsilon_n, then
that diagonal matrix
with a constant diagonal
is the simple Gauss-Markov
assumption, yeah.
Now, I'm sure it
comes as no surprise
that Gaussian distributions
don't always fit everything.
And so one needs to get
clever with extending
the models to other cases.
And there are-- I know--
Laplace distributions, Pareto
distributions, contaminated
normal distributions,
which can be used to
fit regression models.
And these general cases really
extend the applicability
of regression models to
many interesting settings.
So let's turn to specifying
the estimator criterion in two.
So how do we judge what's a
good estimate of the regression
parameters?
Well, we're going to cover least
squares, maximum likelihood,
robust methods, which are
contamination resistant.
And other methods exist
that we will mention but not
get into really in
the lectures, are
Bayes methods and accommodating
incomplete or missing data.
Essentially, as your approach
to modeling a problem
gets more and more
realistic, you
start adding more and more
complexity as it's needed.
And certainly issues
of-- well, robust methods
is where you assume
most of the data
arrives under normal
conditions, but once in a while
there may be some
problem with the data.
And you don't want
your methodology just
to break down if there happens
to be some outliers in the data
or contamination.
Bayes methodologies
are the technology
for incorporating
subjective beliefs
into statistical models.
And I think it's fair
to say that probably
all statistical modeling
is essentially subjective.
And so if you're going to be
good at statistical modeling,
you want to be sure that you're
effectively incorporating
subjective information in that.
And so Bayes methodologies
are very, very useful,
and indeed pretty much
required to engage
in appropriate modeling.
And then finally, accommodate
incomplete or missing data.
The world is always sort
of cruel in terms of you
often are missing what you
think is critical information
to do your analysis.
And so how do you
deal with situations
where you have some
holes in your data?
Statistical models provide
good methods and tools
for dealing with that situation.
OK.
Then let's see.
In case analyses for
checking assumptions,
let me go through this.
Basically when you fit
a regression model,
you check assumptions by
looking at the residuals, which
are the basically estimates of
the epsilons, the deviations
of the dependent variable
from their predictions.
And what one wants
to do is analyze
these to determine whether our
assumptions are appropriate.
OK, but the Gauss-Markov
assumptions would be,
do these appear to
have constant variance?
And it may be that their
variance depends on time,
if the i is indexing time.
Residuals might depend on
the other variables as well,
and one wants to determine
that that isn't the case.
There are also influence
diagnostics identifying cases
which are highly influential.
It turns out that when you
are building a regression
model with data, you
treat all the cases as
if they're equally important.
Well, it may be
that certain cases
are really critical to
estimated certain factors.
And it may be that much of the
inference about how important
a certain factor
is is determined
by very small number of points.
So even though you
have a massive data set
that you're using
to fit a model,
it could be that
some of the structure
is driven by a very
small number of cases.
So influence diagnostics give
you a way of analyzing that.
In the problem set
for this lecture,
you'll be deriving some
influence diagnostics
for linear regression
models and seeing how
they're mathematically defined.
And I'll be distributing
a case study which
illustrates fitting
linear regression
models for asset prices.
And you can see
how those play out
with some practical examples.
OK, finally there's
outlier detection.
With outliers, it's interesting.
The exceptions in data are
often the most interesting.
It's important in
modeling to understand
whether certain
cases are unusual.
And sometimes their
degree of idiosyncrasy
can be explained away
so that one essentially
discards those outliers.
But other times,
those idiosyncrasies
lead to extensions of the model.
And so outlier detection can be
very important for validating
a model.
OK, so with that introduction to
regression, linear regression,
let's talk about
ordinary least squares.
Ah.
OK, the least squares criterion
is for a given a regression
parameter, beta,
which is considered
to be a column vector-- so I'm
taking the transpose of a row
vector.
The least squares criterion
is to basically take
the sum of square deviations
from the actual value
of the response variable
from its linear prediction.
So y_i minus y hat i,
we're just plugging
in for y hat i the
linear function
of the independent variables
and the squaring that.
And the ordinary least
squares estimate, beta hat,
minimizes this function.
So in order to solve for this,
we're going to use matrices.
And so we're going to take
the y vector, the vector of n
values of the
dependent variable,
or the response variable,
and X, the matrix
of values of the
independent variable.
It's important in this
set up to keep straight
that cases go by
rows and columns
go by values of the
independent variable.
Boy, this thing is
ultra sensitive.
Excuse me.
Do I turn off the touchpad here?
OK.
So we can now define
our fitted value, y hat,
to be equal to the
matrix x times beta.
And with matrix multiplication,
that results in the y hat 1
through y hat n.
And Q of beta can basically
be written as y minus X beta
transpose y minus X beta.
So this term here is an
n-vector minus the product
of the X matrix times beta,
which is another n-vector.
And we're just taking the
cross product of that.
And the ordinary least
squares estimate for beta
solves the derivative of
this criterion equaling 0.
Now, that's in
fact true, but who
can tell me why that's true?
Say again?
AUDIENCE: Is that minimum?
PROFESSOR: OK.
So your name?
AUDIENCE: Seth.
PROFESSOR: Seth?
Seth.
Very good, Seth.
Thanks, Seth.
So if we want to
find a minimum of Q,
then that minimum will have,
if it's a smooth function,
will have a minimum
at slope equals 0.
Now, how do we know whether
it's a minimum or not?
It could be a maximum.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: OK, right.
So in fact, this
is a-- Q of beta
is a convex function of beta.
And so its second
derivative is positive.
And if you basically think
about the set-- basically,
this is the first
derivative of Q with respect
to beta equaling 0.
If you were to solve for
the second derivative of Q
with respect to beta,
well, beta is a p-vector.
So the second
derivative is actually
a second derivative
matrix, and that matrix,
you can solve for it.
It will be X
transpose X, which is
a positive definite or
semi-definite matrix.
So it basically had a
positive derivative there.
So anyway, this ordinary
least squares estimates
will solve this d Q of
beta by d beta equals 0.
What does d Q beta by d beta_j?
Well, you just take the
derivative of this sum.
So we're taking the sum
of all these elements.
And if you take the
derivative-- well,
OK, the derivative
is a linear operator.
So the derivative of a sum is
the sum of the derivatives.
So we take the summation out and
we take the derivative of each
term, so we get 2 minus x_(i,j),
then the thing in square
brackets, y_i minus that.
And what is that?
Well, in matrix
notation, if we let
this sort of bold X
sub square j denote
the j-th column of the
independent variables,
then this is minus 2.
Basically, the j-th column of X
transpose times y minus X beta.
So this j-th equation for
ordinary least squares
has that representation in
terms-- in matrix notation.
Now if we put that all
together, we basically
can define this derivative
of Q with respect
to the different
regression parameters
as basically the minus twice
the j-th column stacked times y
minus X beta, which is simply
minus 2 X transpose, y minus X
beta.
And this has to equal 0.
And if we just simplify,
taking out the two,
we get this set of equations.
It must be satisfied by
the ordinary least squares
estimate, beta.
And that's called the
normal equations in books
on regression modeling.
So let's consider
how we solve that.
Well, we can re-express that
by multiplying through the X
transpose on each of the terms.
And then beta hat basically
solves this equation.
And if X transpose
X inverse exists,
we get beta hat is equal
to X transpose X inverse X
transpose y.
So with matrix algebra, we
can actually solve this.
And matrix algebra
is going to be
very important to this
lecture and other lectures.
So if this stuff is-- if
you're a bit rusty on this,
do brush up.
This particular
solution for beta hat
assumes that X transpose
X inverse exists.
Who can tell me
what assumptions do
we need to make for X
transpose X to have an inverse?
I'll call you in a second
if no one else does.
Somebody just said something.
Someone else.
No?
All right.
OK, Will.
AUDIENCE: So X
transpose X inverse
needs to have full
rank, which means
that each of the submatrices
needs to have [INAUDIBLE]
smaller dimension.
PROFESSOR: OK, so Will said,
basically, the matrix X
needs to have full rank.
And so if X has full rank,
then-- well, let's see.
If X has full rank, then the
singular value decomposition
which was in the very
first class can exist.
And you have basically
p singular values
that are all non-zero.
And X transpose X
can be expressed
as sort of a, from the
singular value decomposition,
as one of the orthogonal
matrices times the square
of the singular values times
that same matrix transpose,
if you recall that definition.
So that actually
is-- it basically
provides a solution for X
transpose X inverse, indeed,
from the singular value
decomposition of X.
But what's required is that
you have a full rank in X.
And what that means
is that you can't have
independent variables
that are explained
by other independent variables.
So different columns of
X have to be linear--
or they can't linearly depend
on any other columns of X.
Otherwise, you would
have reduced rank.
So now if beta hat
doesn't have full rank,
then our least squares estimate
of beta might be non-unique.
And in fact, it is
the case that if you
are really interested
in just predicting
values of a dependent
variable, then
having non-unique
least squares estimates
isn't as much of a
problem, because you still
get estimates out of that.
But for now, we want to assume
that there's full column rank
in the independent variables.
All right.
Now, if we plug in the value
of the solution for the least
squares estimate,
we get fitted values
for the response variable, which
are simply the matrix X times
beta hat.
And this expression
for the fitted values
is basically X times X transpose
X inverse X transpose y,
which we can represent as Hy.
Basically, this H matrix in
linear models and statistics
is called the hat matrix.
It's basically a
projection matrix
that takes the linear vector,
or the vector of values
of the response variable,
into the fitted values.
So this hat matrix
is quite important.
The problem set's going
to cover some features,
go into some properties
of the hat matrix.
Does anyone want to make any
comments about this hat matrix?
It's actually a very
special type of matrix.
Does anyone want to point out
what that special type is?
It's a projection matrix, OK.
Yeah.
And in linear algebra,
projection matrices
have some very
special properties.
And it's actually an
orthogonal projection matrix.
And so if you're
interested in that feature,
you should look into that.
But it's really a very rich
set of properties associated
with this hat matrix.
It's an orthogonal projection,
and it's-- let's see.
What's it projecting?
It's projecting from
n-space into what?
Go ahead.
What's your name?
AUDIENCE: Ethan.
PROFESSOR: Ethan, OK.
AUDIENCE: Into space [INAUDIBLE]
PROFESSOR: Basically, yeah.
It's projecting into
the column space of X.
So that's what linear
regression is doing.
So in focusing and
understanding linear regression,
you can think of, how do we
get estimates of this p-vector?
That's all very good and useful,
and we'll do a lot of that.
But you can also
think of it as, what's
happening in the
n-dimensional space?
So you basically
are representing
this n-dimensional vector
y by its projection
onto the column space.
Now, the residuals are
basically the difference
between the response value
and the fitted value.
And this can be expressed
as y minus y hat,
or I_n minus H times y.
And it turns out that I_n minus
H is also a projection matrix,
and it's projecting the data
onto the space orthogonal
to the column space of x.
And to show that that's
true, if we consider
the normal equations, which
are X transpose y minus X beta
hat equaling 0, that basically
is X transpose epsilon hat
equals 0.
And so from the
normal equations,
we can see that
what they mean is
they mean that the residual
vector epsilon hat is
orthogonal to each
of the columns of X.
You can take any column
in X, multiply that
by the residual vector,
and get 0 coming out.
So that's a feature
of the residuals
as they relate to the
independent variables.
OK, all right.
So at this point, we've gone
through really not talking
about any statistical
properties to specify the betas.
All we've done is talked-- we've
introduced the least squares
criterion and said, what
value of the beta vector
minimizes that least
squares criterion?
Let's turn to the
Gauss-Markov theorem
and start introducing some
statistical properties,
probability properties.
So with our data, y and X-- yes?
Yes.
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: That epsilon--
PROFESSOR: OK.
Let me go back to that.
It's that X, the columns
of X, and the column
vector of the residual are
orthogonal to each other.
So we're not doing a
projection onto a null space.
This is just a statement that
those values, or those column
vectors, are orthogonal
to each other.
And just to recap, the
epsilon is a projection of y
onto the space orthogonal
to the column space.
And y hat is a projection
onto the column space of y.
And these projections are
all orthogonal projections,
and so they happen to result in
the projected value epsilon hat
must be orthogonal to
the column space of X,
if you project it out.
OK?
All right.
So the Gauss-Markov theorem,
we have data y and X again.
And now we're going to
think of the observed data,
little y_1 through
y_n, is actually
an observation of the
random vector capital
Y, composed of random
variables Y_1 up to Y_n.
And the expectation
of this vector
conditional on the values
of the independent variables
and their regression
parameters given by X,
beta-- so the dependent
variable vector
has expectation
given by the product
of the independent variables
matrix times the regression
parameters.
And the covariance matrix
of Y given X and beta
is sigma squared
times the identity
matrix, the n-dimensional
identity matrix.
So the identity matrix has
1's along the diagonal,
n-dimensional, and
0's off the diagonal.
So the variances of the Y's
are the diagonal entries,
those are all the
same, sigma squared.
And the covariance between
any two are equal to 0
conditionally.
OK, now the
Gauss-Markov theorem.
This is a terrific result
in linear models theory.
And it's terrific in terms of
the mathematical content of it.
I think it's-- for a math class,
it's really a nice theorem
to introduce you to and
highlight the power of, I
guess, results that can arise
from applying the theory.
And so to set this
theorem up, we
want to think about trying
to estimate some function
of the regression parameters.
And so OK, our problem is
with ordinary least squares--
it was, how do we specify
the regression parameters
beta_1 through beta_p?
Let's consider a general
target of interest,
which is a linear
combination of the betas.
So we want to predict
a parameter theta which
is some linear combination
of the regression parameters.
And because that linear
combination of the regression
parameters corresponds to the
expectation of the response
variable corresponding
to a given
row of the independent
variables matrix,
this is just a
generalization of trying
to estimate the means
of the regression model
at different points
in the space,
or to be estimating other
quantities that might arise.
So this is really a very
general kind of thing
to want to estimate.
It certainly is appropriate
for predictions.
And if we consider the
least squares estimate
by just plugging in beta hat
one through beta hat p, solved
by the least squares,
well, it turns out
that those are an unbiased
estimator of the parameter
theta.
So if we're trying to
estimate this combination
of these unknown parameters,
you plug in the least squares
estimate, you're going to get
an estimator that's unbiased.
Who can tell me
what unbiased is?
It's probably going to be a new
concept for some people here.
Anyone?
OK, well it's a basic
property of estimators
in statistics where the
expectation of this statistic
is the true parameter.
So it doesn't, on average,
probabilistically, it
doesn't over- or
underestimate the value.
So that's what unbiased means.
Now, it's also a
linear estimator
of theta in terms
of this theta hat
being a particular
linear combination
of the dependent variables.
So with our original
response variable y,
in the case of y_1 through
y_n, this theta hat is simply
a linear combination
of all the y's.
And now why is that true?
Well, we know that beta hat,
from the normal equations,
is solved by X transpose
X inverse X transpose y.
So it's a linear
transform of the y vector.
So if we take a
linear combination
of those components, it's also
another linear combination
of the y vector.
So this is a linear
function of the underlying--
of the response variables.
Now, the Gauss-Markov
theorem says
that, if the Gauss-Markov
assumptions apply,
then the estimator theta
has the smallest variance
amongst all linear unbiased
estimators of theta.
So it actually is
like the optimal one,
as long as this is our criteria.
And this is really a
very powerful result.
And to prove it, it's very easy.
Let's see.
Actually, these notes are
going to be distributed.
So I'm going to go through
this very, very quickly
and come back to it later
if we have more time.
But you basically-- the
argument for the proof here
is you consider another
linear estimate which
is also an unbiased estimate.
So let's consider a competitor
to the least squares value
and then look at the difference
between that estimator
and theta hat.
And so that can be characterized
as basically this vector,
f transpose y.
And this difference
in the estimates
must have expectation 0.
So basically, if we look at--
if theta tilde is unbiased,
then this expression
here is going
to be equal to zero,
which means that f--
the difference in
these two estimators, f
defines the difference
in the two estimators--
has to be orthogonal to
the column space of x.
And with this
result, one then uses
this orthogonality of
f and d to evaluate
the variance of theta tilde.
And in this proof, the
mathematical argument
here is really something--
I should put some asterisks
on a few lines here.
This expression here is
actually very important.
We're basically looking
at the decomposition
of the variance to
be the variance of b
transpose y, which is
the variance of the sum
of these two random variables.
So the page before
basically defined d and f
such that this is true.
Now when you consider
the variance of a sum,
it's not the sum
of the variances.
It's the sum of the
variances plus twice
the sum of the covariances.
And so when you are
calculating variances
of sums of random variables,
you have to really keep
track of the covariance terms.
In this case, this
argument shows
that the covariance
terms are, in fact, 0,
and you get the
result popping out.
But that's really a-- in
an econometrics class,
they'll talk about BLUE
estimates of regression,
or the BLUE property of the
least squares estimates.
That's where that comes from.
All right, so let's now consider
generalizing from Gauss-Markov
to allow for unequal variances
and possibly correlated
nonzero covariances
between the components.
And in this case,
the regression model
has the same linear set up.
The only difference
is the expectation
of the residual
vector is still 0.
But the covariance matrix
of the residual vector
is sigma squared,
a single parameter,
times let's say capital sigma.
And we'll assume here
that this capital sigma
matrix is a known n by n
positive definite matrix
specifying relative
variances and correlations
between the observations.
OK.
Well, in order to solve
for regression estimates
under these generalized
Gauss-Markov assumptions,
we can transform the
data Y, X to Y star
equals sigma to the
minus 1/2 y and X
to X star, which is
sigma to the minus 1/2 x.
And this model then becomes
a model, a linear regression
model, in terms of
Y star and X star.
We're basically multiplying
this regression model by sigma
to the minus 1/2 across.
And epsilon star actually
has a covariance matrix
equal to sigma squared
times the identity.
So if we just take a
linear transformation
of the original data,
we get a representation
of the regression
model that satisfies
the original
Gauss-Markov assumptions.
And what we had to
do was basically
do a linear transformation
that makes the response
variables all have constant
variance and be uncorrelated.
So with that, we then have the
least squares estimate of beta
is the least squares, the
ordinary least squares,
in terms of Y star and X star.
And so plugging that in, we then
have X star transpose X star
inverse X star transpose Y star.
And if you multiply through,
that's how the formula changes.
So this formula characterizing
the least squares estimate
under this generalized
set of assumptions
highlights what you
need to do to be
able to apply that theorem.
So with response values that
have very large variances,
you basically want to discount
those by the sigma inverse.
And that's part of the way in
which these generalized least
squares work.
All right.
So now let's turn to
distribution theory
for normal regression models.
Let's assume that
the residuals are
normals with mean 0 and
variance sigma squared.
OK, conditioning on the values
of the independent variable,
the Y's, the response
variables, are
going to be independent
over the index i.
They're not going to be
identically distributed
because they have
different means, mu_i
for the dependent
variable Y_i, but they
will have a constant variance.
And what we can do is
basically condition on X, beta,
and sigma squared
and then represent
this model in terms of the
distribution of the epsilons.
So if we're conditioning
on x and beta,
this X beta is a constant,
known, we've conditioned on it.
And the remaining uncertainty
is in the residual vector,
which is assumed to
be all independent
and identically distributed
normal random variables.
Now, this is the
first time you'll
see this notation, capital N sub
little n, for a random vector.
It's a multivariate
normal random variable
where you consider an n-vector
where each component is
normally distributed,
with mean given
by some corresponding
mean vector,
and a covariance matrix
given by a covariance matrix.
In terms of independent and
identically distributed values,
the probability structure
here is totally well-defined.
Anyone here who's taken a
beginning probability class
knows what the
density function is
for this multivariate
normal distribution
because it's the product
of the independent density
functions for the
independent components,
because they're all
independent random variables.
So this multivariate
normal random vector
has a density function
which you can write down,
given your first
probability class.
OK, here I'm just
highlighting or defining
the mu vector for the means
of the cases of the data.
And the covariance matrix
sigma is this diagonal matrix.
And so basically sigma_(i,j)
is equal to sigma squared times
the Kronecker delta
for the (i,j) element.
Now what we want to do
is, under the assumptions
of normally
distributed residuals,
to solve for the distribution
of the least squares estimators.
We want to know, basically,
what kind of distribution
does it have?
Because what we want
to be able to do
is to determine
whether estimates
are particularly large or not.
And maybe there's
no structure at all
and the regression
parameters are 0 so
that there's no dependence
on a given factor.
And we need to be able to
judge how significant that is.
So we need to know what
the distribution is
of our least squares estimate.
So what we're going to do
is apply moment generating
functions to derive the
joint distribution of y
and the joint
distribution of beta hat.
And so Choongbum introduced
the moment generating function
for individual random variables
for single-variate random
variables.
For n-variate
random variables, we
can define the moment generating
function of the Y vector
to be the expectation of
e to the t transpose Y.
So t is an argument of the
moment generating function.
It's another n-vector.
And it's equal to the
expectation of e to the t_1 Y_1
plus t_2 Y_2 up to t_n Y_n.
So this is a very
simple definition.
Because of independence,
the expectation
of the products, or
this exponential sum
is the product of
the exponentials.
And so this moment
generating function is simply
the product of the moment
generating functions for Y_1
up through Y_n.
And I think-- I don't know if
it was in the first problem set
or in the first lecture, but e
to the t_i mu_i plus a half t_i
squared sigma squared
was the moment generating
function for the
single univariate
normal random variable,
mean mu_i and variance sigma
squared.
And so if we have n of
these, we take their product.
And the moment
generating function
for y is simply e to the
t transpose mu plus 1/2
t transpose sigma t.
And so for this multivariate
normal distribution,
this is its moment
generating function.
And this happens to be--
the distribution of y
is a multivariate normal with
mean mu and covariance matrix
sigma.
So a fact that
we're going to use
is that if we're working with
multivariate normal random
variables, this is the structure
of their moment generating
functions.
And so if we solve for
the moment generation
function of some
other item of interest
and recognize that
it has the same form,
we can conclude that it's also
a multivariate normal random
variable.
So let's do that.
Let's solve for the
moment generation
function of the least
squares estimate, beta hat.
Now rather than dealing
with an n-vector,
we're dealing with a p-vector
of the betas, beta hats.
And this is simply the
definition of the moment
generating function.
If we plug in for basically
what the functional form is
for the ordinary least
squares estimates
and how they depend on
the underlying Y, then we
basically-- OK, we have
A equal to, essentially,
the linear projection of Y.
That gives us the least squares
estimate.
And then we can say that
this moment generating
function for beta hat is
equal to the expectation of e
to the t transpose Y, where
little t is A transpose tau.
Well, we know what this is.
This is the moment
generating function
of X-- sorry, of Y-- evaluated
at the vector little t.
So we just need to plug in
little t, that expression
A transpose tau.
So let's do that.
And you do that and it turns
out to be e to the t transpose
mu plus that.
And we go through a
number of calculations.
And at the end of the day, we
get that the moment generating
function is just e to the tau
transpose beta plus a 1/2 tau
transpose this matrix tau.
And that is the moment
generation function
of a multivariate normal.
So these few lines that you
can go through after class
basically solve for
the moment generating
function of beta hat.
And because we can
recognize this as the MGF
of a multivariate normal, we
know that that's-- beta hat is
a multivariate normal,
with mean the true beta,
and covariance matrix given by
the object in square brackets
there.
OK, so this is
essentially the conclusion
of that previous analysis.
The marginal distribution
of each of the beta hats
is given by beta hat-- by a
univariate normal distribution
with mean beta_j and variance
equal to the diagonal.
Now at this point, saying
that is like an assertion.
But one can actually
prove that very easily,
given this sequence of argument.
And can anyone tell
me why this is true?
Let me tell you.
If you consider plugging in
the moment generating function,
the value tau, where only
the j-th entry is non-zero,
then you have the moment
generating function
of the j-th component
of beta hat.
And that's a Gaussian
moment generating function.
So the marginal distribution of
the j-th component is normal.
So you get that
almost for free from
this multivariate analysis.
And so there's no hand waving
going on in having that result.
This actually follows
directly from the moment
generating functions.
OK, let's now turn
to another topic.
Related, but it's the
QR decomposition of X.
So we have-- with our
independent variables
X, we want to express
this as a product
of an orthonormal matrix
Q which is n by p,
and an upper
triangular matrix R.
So it turns out that any
matrix, n by p matrix,
can be expressed in this form.
And we'll quickly show you
how that can be accomplished.
We can accomplish
that by conducting
a Gram-Schmidt
orthonormalization
of the independent
variables matrix X.
And let's see.
So if we define R, the upper
triangular matrix in the QR
decomposition, to have
0's off the diagonal below
and then possibly nonzero
value along the diagonal
into the right, we're just
going to solve for Q and R
through this
Gram-Schmidt process.
So the first column of X is
equal to the first column
of Q times the first
element, the top left corner
of the matrix R.
And if we take the cross product
of that vector with itself,
then we get this expression
for r_(1,1) squared--
we can basically solve for
r_(1,1) as the square root
of this dot product.
And Q_Q_[1] is simply the first
column of X divided by that
square root.
So this first element
of the Q matrix
and the first element r, this
can be solved for right away.
Then let's solve for
the second column of Q
and the second column
of the R matrix.
Well, X_X_[2], the second
column of the X matrix,
is the first column
of Q times r_(1,2),
plus the second column
of Q times r_(2,2).
And if we multiply this
expression by Q_Q_[1] transpose,
then we basically get this
expression for r_(1,2).
So we actually have
just solved for r_(1,2).
And Q_Q_[2] is solved for by
the arguments given here.
So basically, we successively
are orthogonalizing
columns of X to the
previous columns of X
through this
Gram-Schmidt process.
And it basically can be repeated
through all the columns.
Now with this QR
decomposition, what we get
is a really nice form for
the least squares estimate.
Basically, it simplifies to the
inverse of R times Q transpose
y.
And this basically
means that you
can solve for least squares
estimates by calculating the QR
decomposition, which is a
very simple linear algebra
operation, and then just do
a couple of matrix products
to get the-- well, you do have
to do a matrix inverse with R
to get that out.
And the covariance
matrix of beta hat
is equal to sigma squared
X transpose X inverse.
And in terms of the covariance
matrix, what is implicit here
but you should make
explicit in your study,
is if you consider taking a
matrix, R inverse Q transpose
times y, the only thing that's
random there is that y vector,
OK?
The covariance of a matrix
times a random vector
is that matrix
times the covariance
of the vector times the
transpose of the matrix.
So if you take a
matrix transformation
of a random vector,
then the covariance
of that transformation
has that form.
So that's where this covariance
matrix is coming into play.
And from the MGF, the
moment generating function,
for the least squares
estimate, this basically
comes out of the moment
generating function definition
as well.
And if we take X
transpose X, plug
in the QR decomposition,
only the R's play out,
giving you that.
Now, this also gives
us a very nice form
for the hat matrix,
which turns out
to just be Q times Q transpose.
So that's a very simple form.
So now with the
distribution theory,
this next section is
going to actually prove
what's really a
fundamental result
about normal linear
regression models.
And I'm going to go through
this somewhat quickly just
so that we cover what the
main ideas are of the theorem.
But the details, I think,
are very straightforward.
And these course notes
that will be posted online
will go through the various
steps of the analysis.
OK, so there's an
important theorem here
which is for any
matrix A, m by n,
you consider transforming
the random vector y
by this matrix A. It is
also a random normal vector.
And its distribution
is going to have
a mean and covariance
matrix given
by mu_z and sigma_z, which have
this simple expression in terms
of the matrix A and
the underlying means
and covariances of y.
OK, earlier we actually
applied this theorem
with A corresponding to the
matrix that generates the least
squares estimates.
So with A equal to X
transpose X inverse,
we actually previously went
through the solution for what's
the distribution of beta hat.
And with any other
matrix A, we can
go through the same analysis
and get the distribution.
So if we do that here,
well, we can actually
prove this important
theorem, which
says that with least
squares estimates
of normal linear regression
models, our least
squares estimate beta hat and
our residual vector epsilon hat
are independent
random variables.
So when we construct
these statistics,
they are statistically
independent of each other.
And the distribution of beta
hat is multivariate normal.
The sum of the squared
residuals is, in fact,
a multiple of a chi-squared
random variable.
Now who in here can tell me what
a chi-squared random variable
is?
Anyone?
AUDIENCE: [INAUDIBLE]?
PROFESSOR: Yes, that's right.
So a chi-squared random variable
with one degree of freedom
is a squared normal zero
one random variable.
A chi-squared with
two degrees of freedom
is the sum of two independent
normals, zero one, squared.
And so the sum of n squared
residuals is, in fact,
an n minus p chi-squared random
variable scale it by sigma
squared.
And for each component
j, if we take
the difference between the least
squares estimate beta hat j
and beta_j and divide
through by this estimate
of the standard
deviation of that, then
that will, in fact, have a
t distribution on n minus p
degrees of freedom.
And let's see, a t distribution
in probability theory
is the ratio of a normal random
variable to an independent chi
squared random variable, or
the root of an independent chi
squared random variable.
So basically these
properties characterize
our regression parameter
estimates and t statistics
for those estimates.
Now, OK, in the
course notes, there's
a moderately long proof.
But all the details
are given, and I'll
be happy to go through any
of those details with people
during office hours.
Let me just push
on to-- let's see.
We have maybe two minutes
left in the class.
Let me just talk about
maximum likelihood estimation.
And in fitting models
and statistics,
maximum likelihood estimation
comes up again and again.
And with normal linear
regression models,
it turns out that ordinary
least squares estimate
are, in fact, our maximum
likelihood estimates.
And what we want to do
with a maximum likelihood
is to maximize.
We want to define the
likelihood function, which
is the density function
for the data given
the unknown parameters.
And this density
function is simply
the density function for a
multivariate normal random
variable.
And the maximum
likelihood estimates
are the estimates of the
underlying parameters
that basically maximize
the density function.
So it's the values of
the underlying parameters
that make the data that was
observed the most likely.
And if you plug in the values
of the density function,
basically we have these
independent random variables,
Y_i, whose product
is the joint density.
The likelihood
function turns out
to be basically a function of
the least squares criterion.
So if you fit models
by least squares,
you're consistent with doing
something decent in at least
applying the maximum
likelihood principle
if you had a normal
linear regression model.
And it's useful to know when
your statistical estimation
algorithms are consistent
with certain principles
like maximum likelihood
estimation or others.
So let me, I guess,
finish there.
And next time, I will
just talk a little bit
about generalized M estimators.
Those provide a
class of estimators
that can be used for
finding robust estimates
and also quantile estimates
of regression parameters
which are very interesting.